<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Work | Ged's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.gedrap.me/blog/categories/work/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.gedrap.me/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-19T15:57:20+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.gedrap.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gediminas Rapolavicius]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[4 things I learned the hard way while freelancing]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.gedrap.me/blog/2014/05/19/4-things-i-learned-the-hard-way-while-freelancing/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-19T15:20:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.gedrap.me/blog/2014/05/19/4-things-i-learned-the-hard-way-while-freelancing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>During the first two years of freelancing, I discovered a bunch of things that I wish I knew before. So this is me, time travelling back to the past and teaching the younger self how to have great time while freelancing.</p>

<h2>1. Use retainer contracts for your own good</h2>

<p>First time I read about the retainers on <a href="https://training.kalzumeus.com/newsletters/archive/services_vs_products">Patrick&rsquo;s newsletter</a>, I thought it&rsquo;s something just for fancy top contractors charging many times more than  I do. A few clients later, I realised how wrong I was.</p>

<p>Happy clients want more and more. They love your products, and when they have some extra cash, they don&rsquo;t mind spending some of it for new features. And that&rsquo;s awesome! But the great feeling of being important quickly fades away when you find yourself switching between 3 clients, most of the time is spent on maintenance and the workload is irregular. One month, you just need to spend an evening to slightly change the styling. The other month you have a huge list of new features (because the client loves what you have already done ;) ). Retainer comes her to save a day (and maybe even your sanity!).</p>

<p>For an agreed amount of money, you guarantee that you will available for some given number of hours/days/weeks.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s win-win for everyone. You get some guaranteed income and the client is happy knowing you will be available.</p>

<p>Agree on it now for a happier tomorrow.</p>

<h2>2. Do whatever makes you happy. It&rsquo;s the best investment.</h2>

<p>As a student, I tried to save up money by limiting my spendings. No more daily visits to Starbucks, etc. Because it&rsquo;s wasted money which coulbe be spent on something more important, isn&rsquo;t it? No, it isn&rsquo;t. It&rsquo;s an investment in yourself ;) If taking a break for coffee or a sushi bar makes you happy and you can produce a couple of extra hours (or even an hour) of good work, why the hell not? Amazing ROI, after all.</p>

<h2>3. Take a break and don&rsquo;t feel guilty about it</h2>

<p>I am fortunate enough to be busy and have tasks waiting for my attention all the time. Which, again, sounds great but after a while it can be mounting a lot of pressure. The worst time to feel pressure is when you are trying to rest. You don&rsquo;t get good rest and the feeling of guilt that you aren&rsquo;t working sucks, you continue your work tired, not everything gets done&hellip; And a few months later you are feeling like a zombie. It sucks.</p>

<p>What I found works for me is having some time slots when I don&rsquo;t work no matter how busy I am. Also, no more late nights (or nearly all nighters) to make up for a bad day. No one is productive at night after a long day so no need to be fooling yourself :)</p>

<h2>4. Ugly task which you were postponing for a long time? Have a <a href="http://pomodorotechnique.com/">Pomodoro</a>.</h2>

<p>I found Pomodoro technique very effective when I know I must get this done soon but there are millions of things I would prefer doing. Knowing that you are not stuck in there forever, and soon you will have a break feels great. The default 25mins for work and 5mins for a break works great for me because usually 25mins is long enough to do something meaningful, and 5mins are not too long to get distracted.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it for now. I intentionally avoided topics such as good sleep, healthy food or not allowing family, friends or flat mates to distract you while working from home as they were discussed many times and I am not sure if there is anything I can add to it. I hope you liked and if you read that much already, you should follow me on <a href="https://twitter.com/gedrap">Twitter</a> for more of the same :)</p>

<p>P.S. Everyone is telling you to charge the double you are charging now. Yes, do it. Just do it. You have no idea how underpaid you are (and will cry once you realise).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
